Ricardo Saavedra

Product Designer

ricardosaavedra.io ricardoasaavedra@gmail.com Berlin, Remote

I'm a product designer and recognized thought leader with over a decade of industry experience. As a lead product designer at Meta's Horizon Workrooms, I work to improve the way we meet online and get work done in Virtual Reality. I have a track record of delivering empathic design and business results; previously, I helped co-found Wonder (overseeing product design and strategy) and led cross-functional design teams at Samsung Mobile Lab. I have designed and launched successful products with large organizations and have innovated with startups to roll out new ventures worldwide, often working from initial concepts to later stages of product maturity.

Experience

Meta/Reality Labs

Lead Designer

2022 - Current

I collaborate with researchers to better understand user needs in VR and work closely with engineers to prototype new solutions that substantially improve the UX in productivity use cases in VR/AR. Projects include Magic Rooms (featured by Mark Zuckerberg at Connect 2022) and AR-based interaction patterns shipped with the new Meta Quest Pro. My contributions have had short-term product impacts while also influencing future redesigns and hardware development.

Wonder

Principle Designer

2020 - 2022

As the principal designer and part of the founding team, I worked with key product stakeholders to identify and execute complex product challenges to deliver a superior experience in online gatherings. I led product design initiatives spanning user growth & retention, branding, strategy, design system, and design hiring and mentorship. My contributions allowed the company to reach product-market fit in 16 months, going from an almost zero audience to getting 1M users monthly.

Independent Product Designer

2017 - 2020

As an independent designer, I worked with startups and founders to drive the creation of new products in the AI/ML and Web3 space. Most notably, I helped Status.im to design and launch its crypto wallet and messaging app and helped to co-found the non-profit The Metagovernance Project with Creative Commons' co-creator Lawrence Lessig.

Samsung

UX Design Lead

2012 - 2015

I led a multi-disciplinary team of designers to research and developed many concepts in mobile and wearable computing and contributed to the design of 2 successful product launches, impacting more than 200m users worldwide. I contributed to UX design for the Gear S and Galaxy Tab and played a crucial role in redesigning Samsung mobile OS. As a design lead, I was responsible for the concept and design of two wearable cameras, including many IPs connected to photo capture/management.

Globo.com

Senior Information Architect

2011 - 2012

I led the design and development of mobile products for the leading network conglomerate in South America (Globo.com), collectively reaching 800k downloads. I led a team of designers and engineers from product discovery to 3 Successful launches. Most notably, the award-winning Globo Sports iPad app – a first-of-its-kind companion app – allowed users to watch soccer while experiencing in-game statistics. With 300k downloads, the app was in the Brazilian App Store's top apps of the year.

Education

Strelka Institute

Researcher in-residency

2019

Mills College

MFA in Generative Art and Computational Design

2015 - 2017

University of Rio

MA in Interaction Design and Information Architecture

2011 - 2012

Catholic

University of Rio de Janeiro

BA in Communication and Media Studies

2004 - 2008